Finding Aid for Ross J. Wilhelm Papers, 1925-1983
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ross J. Wilhelm Papers 1925-1983
Wilhelm, Ross Johnston, 1920-1983.
3 linear ft.
85449 Aa 2
Professor of business economics in the University of Michigan School of Business Administration. Copies of radio commentaries, "Business Review," 1960-1981; papers relating to newspaper column, "Inside Business"; speeches and essays; correspondence, 1971-1982; and photographs and miscellaneous.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Wilhelm collection was donated by Mrs. Rowena Wilhelm (Donor no. 7016 ) in 1984. Additions were received in 1988.
The collection is open to research.
Professor Ross Johnston Wilhelm, a University of Michigan business economics professor whose commentaries on business and political issues were nationally syndicated, was born January 20, 1920 in Arlington, New Jersey. He married Rowena May in 1944.
Wilhelm received his BA and MBA degrees from Western Reserve, Cleveland, Ohio and his Ph.D. from the University of Michigan in 1963. Wilhelm was a Professor of Business Economics in the Graduate School of Business Administration at the University of Michigan.
His radio program, "Business Review" was heard from 1961 to 1981 on WUOM, and was nationally syndicated. He also wrote a column "Inside Business" which appeared regularly in more than 300 newspapers. Wilhelm received the University of Michigan Distinguished Service Award in 1963, and the Janus Award for the best business-oriented radio program in the nation in 1973.
Wilhelm died on March 22, 1983, at age 63.
The Ross Wilhelm papers (1925-1982) date principally from 1960 to 1982 and measure three linear feet. The papers document Wilhelm's radio program "Business Review" and other aspects of his professional career.
Subjects:
Economics.; Radio broadcasting--United States.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Broadcasting.; Oak Island (Lunenburg, N.S.); University of Michigan--Faculty.; WUOM (Radio station: Ann Arbor, Mich.); Wilhelm, Ross Johnston, 1920-1983.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal and Biographical, 1925-1982 (scattered dates)
  The Personal and Biographical material (1925-1982) primarily documents Wilhelm's teaching career at the University of Michigan. Included are photographs.
  - General (Box 1)
  - Photos, 2 folders (Box 1)
    Portrait and contact photographs of Wilhelm; photographs of Wilhelm broadcasting WUOM radio program, with students and colleagues, and with family after receiving honorary doctorate from Eastern Michigan University (1977); and slides relating to excavations on Oak Island in Nova Scotia.
- Professional Activities, 1960-1982
  Professional Activities (1960-1982) contains the weekly commentaries Wilhelm gave on his radio show "Business Review." There are also essays and correspondence relating to a column, "Inside Business," that Wilhelm wrote for Business Roundtable, a non-profit organization in New York. Also included are various speeches Wilhelm gave and essays he wrote throughout his career.
  - Business Review, 1960-1969, 10 folders (Box 1)
  - Business Review, 1970-1981 and undated, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Business Roundtable, 1974-1977, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Readings in the Age of Enterprise (book), 1964 (Box 2)
  - Menominee-Marinette Study, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Speeches and Essays
    - 1956-1982 (Box 3)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence, 1971-1982, includes reactions of listeners to "Business Review," greetings from ex-students and documentation of other professional activities.
  - General, 1971-1982 [A-Z], 20 folders (Box 3)
  - Re: Speeches, 1963-1982 (Box 3)
  - Rowena Wilhelm: Condolences received on Ross Wilhelm's death (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous includes notes and an article by Wilhelm on Oak Island, a small island in Nova Scotia where treasure was thought to have been buried. Also included are two folders of newspaper clippings regarding Wilhelm's economic forecasts and political views.
  - Oak Island Treasure, 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1972-1980, 2 folders (Box 3)